<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The maiden-head lost by moon-light, or, The adventure of the meadow written by Joseph Kepple.</title>
            <author>Kepple, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K332A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369385</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">187972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09340)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2851:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The maiden-head lost by moon-light, or, The adventure of the meadow written by Joseph Kepple.</title>
                  <author>Kepple, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniel Brooke at the Angel in cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXII. [1672]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Romance poetry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Youth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:3"/>
            <p>THE MAIDEN-HEAD LOST BY Moon-light: OR THE ADVENTURE OF THE MEADOW.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> JOSEPH KEPPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Brooke</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> MDCLXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:4"/>
            <head>TO THE LADIES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> have in this Romance in <hi>Querpo</hi> (although I believe having read it, you will allow it a better Title, and at least, ſwear 'tis pity it was not True) the perfect Repreſentation of the ſtate of <hi>Innocence;</hi> I don't mean the time when our firſt Parents, for want of Drapers, made uſe of Leaves, but the Age that not long after follow'd; in which <hi>Love,</hi> which is now made a piece of Art, was Natural; when Mens Affections were not byaſs'd with the Deſire of a great Eſtate, and without huge heaps of Gold were contented with the innocent light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Miſtreſſes, I mean that Air, Mine and Gayety they eſteem'd, and did not as we do, cenſure their ſprightly Geſtures, as if Mirth and Honeſty were inconſistent. Then how would they have laugh'd to hear
<pb facs="tcp:187972:5"/>of a Lady, that made her Servant follow the Sent two whole Years, when perhaps ſhe is more in love with the Gallant, than he with her, who in his apiſh Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip (for he must be a Slave to her Will) has ſpent more Money in the <hi>Mulberry Garden,</hi> and the <hi>Parks,</hi> than would build an <hi>Hoſpital;</hi> has ſeen more <hi>Plays</hi> than are good, and been acquainted with all the Coach-men in Town; whoſe Eſtate at last being ſpent <hi>Victoria, Victoria,</hi> the Day's our own, he at last has vanquiſh'd his Miſtreſſes Affections, is marry'd, and with her Portion is just fluſh'd for the viſit of another Lady; and then who can blame our <hi>Prophetick Gentlewomen?</hi> They are like to enjoy little Pleaſure, after the Man in black has conjur'd them together, except to tell how many <hi>Rheniſh-wine</hi> Glaſſes have been drank in drinking her <hi>Health,</hi> by the Good-man her Husband, whow is now perhaps, lest he ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get his Courtſhip, paying his <hi>Devoirs</hi> to new Madam; I know the Ladies having read it (But not for the good of the Book-ſeller, let us contrive how that may be; why, it is but feeing the Chambermaid to pretend Ignorance, and get the Foot Boy-to buy her the new Book of the Maid that was ſo Blind as to Loſe her ſelf in a <hi>Moon ſhine Night,</hi> and then convey it to her Lady, who will by the Title, expect it ſhould be horrible Bawdy, when a ſtarch'd Puritan I think would not groan in Spirit to be call'd the Owner of it) I ſay the Ladies that read it will be curſed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with me, that <hi>Myrtilla</hi> was ſo eaſily gain'd, and that ſhe did not, like our fooliſh Females, oppoſe, what ſhe most deſir'd. For the first I dare oppoſe
<pb facs="tcp:187972:5"/>her Conſtancy to any of their Ladyſhips; and for the other, you ſhall ſee I am ſo much a Gentleman, as to help a young Lady over the Stile. I know her Accuſers Argument is, that ſhe ought to have taken ſome time to try her Servants Affection; but pray direct me to that fooliſh Fop (and I'le procure him a Miſtreſs of Clouts, for he deſerves no better) who when he is wooing, will offer to be deficient in his Duty, that will quarrel at an angry look, and will threaten to bang her if ſhe will not ſay ſhe loves, which is as ridiculous to think, as that a lame Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſhould Hector out an Alms. For my part, I think our <hi>Myrtilla</hi> is to be commended for her Policy, ſhe does by this oblige her Lover, and he must bely the ſhape of a man, and be worſe than a Devil, that will wrong a Lady that ſo confidently commits her Honour to his keeping. Well, however the Ladies quarrel at me and <hi>Myrtilla, Circe</hi> and I ſhall be ſure to ſcape with the Chambermaids, their good hearts will only envy a little her fortune, and it may be ſay their Prayers every Night, and lie croſs-legg'd in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the like.</p>
            <p>It is now fit to tell you why I undertook this harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs piece of Mirth, which was for this Reaſon; I ſaw how well one Story out of the ſame Authour took, beeing turn'd into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that is out of the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Erycius Puteanus,</hi> and thinking this no way infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to it in it ſelf, having nothing to do, I adventur'd upon the Tranſlation of it. I confeſs it comes ſo ſhort of the Pen of that ingenious perſon that wrote the other, that fear I have done the witty <hi>Italian</hi> an unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb facs="tcp:187972:6"/>Injury in daring to render it ſo pitifully. But to excuſe him of all thoſe faults my Tranſlation may make him ſeem guilty of, I aſſure you the Cloaths are my own; If you ask why I made 'em no better, I aſſure you I could not, 'twas done for the aforeſaid Reaſon to avoid idleneſs, and then I think I am a little more excuſable, than the perſon that having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do, went and hir'd in the Market a Drudgery at the expence of a great Sum. If I have offended the Ladies, I beg their pardon, and aſſure them that I am their</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Humble Servant,</hi> J. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187972:6"/>
            <head>THE MAIDEN-HEAD LOST BY Moon-light. OR, <hi>The Adventure of the Meadow.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y little Skill in Geography will not let me give you any better Account, then that in part of the Dominions of the great <hi>Comus,</hi> dwelt a young Gentleman, by Name <hi>Chereſtratus;</hi> I ſhall not trouble my ſelf nor you with a tedious Relation of his Anceſtors, and how many of them were <hi>Lord Mayors;</hi> but I am ſomething like a Woman, and now I think, on't can't but tell you that one of them was hang'd, which I had not done, but that I thought it would not be any diſparagement to him, who was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:187972:7"/>ſo well accompliſh'd, that his firſt actions had quitted the diſgrace had they all ſuffer'd the like fate; He was not at all behind hand with the Gallants of theſe times, either for Learning or Valour, beſides Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and compoſing of Madrigals, which ſeemed in thoſe days to have been in great uſe; for the Ladies being not over coy, were not ſo great Enemies to the Progreſs of Muſick, as to deny themſelves or Servant the pleaſure of an early <hi>Serenade,</hi> which the next day was rewarded with ſome ſignal favour, except the Lady ſo courted had been wak'd out of ſome pleaſant Dream, and then too ſhe durſt hardly chide, for fear left being out with the men (who where chiefly concern'd in the Comedy) her Dream ſhould prove but a Dream, and ſhe ſhould never be made happy with the Reality. Beſides this, he could Dance incomparably well, by which the Ladies might gheſs he had not been under the Surgeon's hands, nor had much skill in <hi>Maiden heads</hi> (a thing very much to be deplor'd in our days, for our Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants not finding the firſt night what they look for (but they are fools that do) ſeldome continue Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving above the firſt Month; and ſeem not ſo much to be married as to keep a Miſtreſs with a little more Ceremony. I am loath to tell you that with theſe Perfections he was rich, for I would be unwilling to put in any thing that might make you ſuſpect the truth of this Relation, and I am ſure you will never believe, that a perſon ſo well accompliſh'd, and of a ſufficient Eſtate ſhould find ſo cruel a Lady, as not to admit of his Addreſſes. But you muſt conſider the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:187972:7"/>time which according to the beſt Chronologers was in <hi>Tireſias</hi>'s days, and the women would not deny his Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> That they take as much pleaſure or more in doing the Gentleman a good turn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than the perſon that receiv'd it, This made the Ladies then, contrary to what they are now a days, count it an unpardonable Sin to take a Reward for their mutual pleaſures, and this made <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> not prove ſo ſucceſsfull in his Amours, as he might have done had he liv'd now.</p>
            <p>But to come to the Story, it was the unhappineſs of this incomparable Gallant, to place his Affection on a Perſon that diſdain'd his frequent Suits, which ſhe did with a kind of Reluctancy, for ſhe her ſelf nor any body elſe could tell why ſhe would not let him pay his <hi>Devoirs</hi> to her, as well as any other Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant of the Town, to whom he was no way inferiour. But the myſteries of Love are as blind as himſelf, whoſe hidden Cauſes can never be underſtood, and I ſhould rather be content to be kept in ignorance, then endeavour of a diſcovery of <hi>Medea's Video me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora proboque, Deteriora ſequor.</hi> However the Lady continued very obſtinate, whether becauſe ſhe was prepoſſeſs'd with the Love of <hi>Hyleus</hi> (Rival only in Love to our noble <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> for, for other things he could not ſtand in competition with him) or for ſome other Reaſon, I know not. For I do not think that the comparing of a Ladie's Favours to Shadows always holds true, for then <hi>Hyleus</hi> had been as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy as our unfortunate Gentleman, who ply'd his Buſineſs as hotly as <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> could poſſibly do.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:187972:8"/>
            <p>By this time <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> was grown a perfect Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of Love, which made him like the reſt of that mad Religion abandon the ſociety of men, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring as it were to be free from himſelf, he would often be ſinging ſome lamentable Ditty, of which he had ſtore, but above all, this was the chief:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whatever I think or whatever I do,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My</hi> Phillis <hi>is ſtill in my mind:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When in anger I mean not to</hi> Phillis <hi>to go</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My feet of themſelves the way find,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now you'l ſay this is very like a modern Song of ours, but I aſſure you what follows, could I but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, was not at all like it, and it was only by chance, that he thought of the firſt Stave, for it is certain there are common notions, which are obvious to all that make upon the ſame Subject. In hitting on which ſome have been ſo happy, that they have wrote whole Poems, and things of greater bulk ſo like other men, that if compar'd, it was not eaſily told which was which. But let this paſs, ſometimes you ſhould have our <hi>Inamorato</hi> under the reverend ſhade of a well ſpread Oak, beſeeching it's ſenſeleſs Divinity to give him leave to inſcribe the Name of his dear <hi>Myrtilla</hi> there (for ſo was the hard-hearted Lady call'd,) and then taking out a Pen Knife, which had never been put to any ſervile office, as cutting of Corns, or the like, he ingraves on the bark with flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Letters, which ſearce a Writing Maſter in thoſe parts could mend, the Name of his Saint. This
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:187972:8"/>done like a meer heatheniſh Gentleman he falls down, and worſhips the work of his own hands; then with a tedious Harangue he twits the poor Tree in the teeth of the benefit he had done it, ſaying that it ſhould be now more famous for bearing the Name of the incomparable <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> then it was for <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and that were not corn yet found out, he might not at all fear a rape of his ripe Acorns, for as ſoon as people came, and ſaw thoſe Letters, rapt up in admiration, they would forget to eat, and with fixed eyes gaze till ſome envious Dryades forc'd 'em from their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. Beſides theſe works of ſupererogation, our Gallant (which was the only comfort he had) was almoſt continually walking by the door of the cruel Lady, whom he ſeem'd to watch or rather guard with as much diligence, as <hi>Argus</hi> did <hi>Io,</hi> or the mortify'd Ghoſt of ſome lately departed Uſurer his muſty baggs, but yet he durſt not (as being forbid by his Miſtreſs, and fearing to diſpleaſe her) hang Garlands at her Poſts ſo artificially woven with Enigmatical Flowers, that ſhe might there read his fervent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. This and ſeveral other Love-tricks that the Youths of thoſe times us'd, to accompliſh their wiſhes, he was forc'd to forbear.</p>
            <p>His Friends by this began to have ſmall hopes of his Eſtate, or Legacies; for his not eating nor drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, made them ſuſpect he was grown im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. Amongſt the reſt of his acquaintance one <hi>Paneutus</hi> a Yeoman ith' Country ſome ten miles of the City where our pining Lover now was, hearing of the deplorable condition his Friend lay in, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:187972:9"/>being himſelf a boon Companion, did not doubt, but if he could get him into the Countrey, he cou'd make him quit his humour. To effect which he wrote this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Paneutus</hi> to his <hi>Chereſtratus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>RAther then ſuſpect your wiſdome, I muſt needs think, that the Lady, which hath brought you into the ſad condition I hear you are in, muſt needs be one of ſo divine a Beauty, that ſhe would make</hi> Cato <hi>in love with her, and convert the ſeverest Woman-hater. However, I am ſo far Intereſs'd in you, as my ſecond ſelf, that knowing a Remedy, I could not but preſcribe it you, which being follow'd will either make you happy with your Love, or without it. Your City Air will ſomething obſtruct the Cure, and hinder your Phyſick from working. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you will accept of my Houſe, you know you may command</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Paneutus.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:187972:9"/>
            <p>This Letter in <hi>Chereſtratus</hi>'s abſence, arriv'd at his City Houſe, who was juſt now gone, as his cuſtome was, to take a view of his Lady's Lodgings, which he did ſo eagerly, that he had like to have paid for his gaping. For ſome of the Neighbours obſerving him how narrowly he ey'd the Houſe, thinking he had ſome bad deſign, acquainted the old Gentlewoman, Mother to the young Lady; who could hardly be perſwaded from carrying our Gallant before the Juſtice, to which her Daughter encourag'd her, which went to the very heart of <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> for ſhe knew well enough though ſhe ſeem'd ignorant of the cauſe. But the old Lady, having no witneſs to prove any thing, diſmiſs'd him, with a ſevere charge never to trouble her door again. What remains now to the deſperate Lover, but to make away with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and fall a Sacrifice to her diſdain? which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he had done, had not his haſty deſire to viſit <hi>Myrtilla's</hi> Houſe made him forget to put on his Shaſh, that morning. A thouſand miſerable thoughts offer'd themſelves to him in his way home, whither he was no ſooner come, but throwing himſelf upon his Bed, he began to bewail his hard fortune, with tears and ſighs. Scarce had he begun his Soliloquy, but his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant came into the Room, and preſented him with the Letter; which having read, and taking a turn or two in the Chamber, the reflecting on his Lady's inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities made him reſolve to accept his Friend's Offer. To which end ſetling his Houſhold Affairs, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all things to be made ready for his next days intended Journey, which accordingly he took, wiſely
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:187972:10"/>chooſing rather to ride a mile about, then to come by <hi>Myrtilla's</hi> Houſe, by which he ſhould have paſſed; being ſafe come to his journey's end we will leave him with his merry Friend <hi>Paneutus,</hi> who entertain'd him with all the kindneſs imaginable, always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring his diverſion with ſome paſtime, as Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hunting, and the like, and return to <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> whoſe Mother you muſt know, knowing what care and caution is to be us'd over young Maids, made the Daughter grow weary of her Government, counting it too ſevere, as depriving her of thoſe Pleaſures that young Ladies would willingly accept of. For her Mother keeping a Dairy would often ſet her to make Butter and Cheeſe for fear of the green Sickneſs, which he knew how to cure as well as any Doctor in <hi>Europe,</hi> had her Mother been as willing as ſhe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſhe had rather have been reading of ſome brisk Romance, or Story of the ſtrange Metamorphoſis of a Maid into a Woman. Beſides her Mother began now to oppoſe <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s Viſits, the only comfort her Daughter had, for ſhe being a pretty while in her Teens, had the ſame deſire as all her Contemporaries had, to mind nothing but the end for which they were made, which caus'd her, encourag'd by her Mothers rigour, to think on ſome way to obtain her deſires, and free her ſelf from the old Lady's Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which was very much encreas'd ſince the death of her Husband, to whoſe Education he left his Girl <hi>Myrtilla.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Long you may imagine ſhe had not ſtudied before ſhe found out a Plot (for Women's Wits on ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:187972:10"/>occaſions are very quick, and for my part I believe that had not <hi>Jupiter</hi> quickly put in Execution his golden Project, <hi>Danae</hi> for all the Tower would have found the way to his Embraces:) well a Plot is now found, which was this, to venture her Maiden-head into <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s hands, rather then endure the ſlavery ſhe was in. This ſhe reſolv'd to put in practice, and contrary to a Woman, kept conſtant too. But ſhe ſaw no way of effecting it without making ſome body privy to it, and then ſhe thought no one fitter then her Maid <hi>Circe,</hi> a loving Girle, and welwiſher to Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, for before ſhe happen'd into her Miſtreſſes Service, ſhe waited on a Lady, and like the reſt of that trade, very often choſe before her Miſtreſs, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe would not ſpeak a good word for a Gallant. <hi>Myrtilla's</hi> Mother being call'd to a Womans Labour, ſhe thought it a very fit time to communicate her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to her Maid. Where upon coming down to look for <hi>Circe</hi> ſhe found her in the Garden tumbling on a Camomile bed, lying on her back a Star-gazing, but ſeeing her young Miſtreſs ſtarting up ſhe quickly quitted that poſture, and ask'd her if ſhe had any ſervice to command her. Ah <hi>Circe</hi> (ſaid ſhe ſighing) I have, could I but be aſſur'd of thy Secrecy. Of mine, Madam? (reply'd <hi>Circe</hi>) why, there be a great many Gallants in Town, would be Surety for me if need requir'd. Why, 'tis the only thing I am good for. Why then (ſaid <hi>Myrtilla</hi> ſitting down with her Maid) you muſt needs have obſerv'd how my Mother pryes into all my Actions, debarring me of all I take delight in. I have now thought how to mend this,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:187972:11"/>would'ſt thou conſent to aid and aſſiſt me. <hi>Circe,</hi> who now thought ſhe ſhould get an opportunity to be reveng'd on her old Miſtreſs for making her riſe ſo early, not admitting of her Sweet-hearts company, and hindring her from wearing her beſt Clothes, and going to Church a Sunday (for let me tell you Preaching is of very old ſtanding) made all Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions poſſible to give her Miſtreſs a good opinion of her Secrecy, which <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> being put to a ſtrait, ſoon believ'd, and ask'd her what ſhe thought of running away with <hi>Hyleus,</hi> without her Mothers conſent. To which <hi>Circe</hi> anſwered, I believe he is an honeſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and were it to me I ſhould take his word; now all the difficulty will be to make him acquainted with the Deſign. For that too (crys <hi>Myrtilla</hi>) I've contriv'd, and now my Mother's out of the way thou ſhalt be the happy Meſſenger to inform my dear <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus</hi> of mine Intent. I am certain he will gladly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the opportunity, which I would never have given him, but that I'm confident his Honour will not let him ſtain mine. Mad <hi>Circe</hi> would have taken up her Miſtreſs, but the ſhort time ſhe had, fearing her Mother's return, would not let <hi>Myrtila</hi> admit of her fooling. Take here ſaid ſhe, this Jewel (in which was neatly wrought in Diamonds) the Story of the Rape of <hi>Proſerpine</hi> by <hi>Pluto,</hi> (and you cannot imagine <hi>Hyleus</hi> ſo much a fool as not at firſt ſight to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Hieroglyphick) which I have got wrought on purpoſe. Deliver it to him as a token of my Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (dear Creature) and tell him I ſhall with impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience expect his coming to fetch me away at Night.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:187972:11"/>
               <hi>Circe,</hi> who was not a ſtranger to theſe Love Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, willingly apply'd her ſelf to her Task immediately, took her Pattins and away to <hi>Hyleus,</hi> who was not at home juſt when ſhe came, but the Servants told her he would be preſently. It was the Butlers fortune to ſee her firſt, who ſeeing her young and handſome, could not but offer the Civility of the Cellar. <hi>Circe</hi> was very willing to accept his offer, the weather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot, and having come a good way, ſhe took off her Liquor, that the Butler began to conceive ſome hopes from the effect of the Drink. But they were ſcarce acquainted, when <hi>Hyleus</hi> came in from Fiſhing, and preſently <hi>Circe</hi> deliver'd her meſſage very diligently, and if I am not very much miſtaken, 'twas juſt thus: Sir, my Lady, Madam <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> by me acquaints you ſhe hath hitherto endeavour'd to find out the means of rewarding your Affection and conſtancy, which you may aſſure your ſelf had been done before this, but that the old Gentlewoman her Mother hath ſuch an averſion to any thing that ſhe hath an inclination for, and ſeeing there is no way to quit ſcores with you but by running away, ſhe doth this night intend to make her ſelf happy with your good company, and for a token of her Love ſhe hath ſent you this Jewel, and deſires you not to fail waiting for her with a Horſe, at her Mother's door, where you may privately carry away your own <hi>Myrtilla.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This unexpected News was extreamly ſurpriſing to <hi>Hyleus,</hi> who before was much fretted with the ſport he but juſt now came from, for his ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in it. And is it ſo then, ye kind Deities (cry'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:187972:12"/>he out) that my <hi>Myrtilla</hi> will thus freely put her ſelf into my hands. I ſhould never deſerve any ſucceſs in my Love, ſhould I neglect this happineſs. Nor am I one of thoſe fooliſh foppiſh Lovers, who having lay'd ſiege to a Ladies Affections, then begin to throw of all reſpect, when ſhe begins to throw off all her cruelty, and when ſhe is coming to anſwer their expectations. Then turning to <hi>Circe,</hi> Aſſure the divine <hi>Myrtylla</hi> from me, I will not fail to expect her, and am only ſorry that ſhe order'd nothing more difficult, that ſhe might ſee my Love in daring to compaſs it; take this (continu'd he giving her a Piece, and then kiſſing her) and carry this Kiſs to thy Miſtreſs, and aſſure her again I will not fail.</p>
            <p>With this Anſwer departed <hi>Circe,</hi> who was got home before ſhe was aware, who was extreamly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with <hi>Hyleus,</hi> and thinking on the Token ſhe had for <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> whom ſhe now began to envy, and long as much for the forbidden fruit as her Miſtreſs; coming to <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> ſhe told her the good ſucceſs of her Meſſage, and how effectually it had wrought upon the Heart of <hi>Hyleus,</hi> who would not fail two hours after Sun-ſet; this done ſhe enter'd on the not unpleaſant Panegyrick of the expected Gentleman. The ill connection of it, as all other Chambermaids diſcourſes, makes me I can't remember it, only this I am ſure was in it, that he was a fine proper Man, handſom Leg'd, and ſhe'd warrant as good a Woman's Man as any in the Shire. But the old Lady coming home made her unwillingly break off her Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyleus</hi> by this time had got all things in readineſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:187972:12"/>for his Love-adventure, and ſetting out with two Servants he had towards the City, which was about three miles from his Houſe, his great deſire of the Prey made him there ſomething of the ſooneſt, which he had not been, but that <hi>Myrtilla</hi> and <hi>Circe</hi> were at difference; for her Miſtreſs could not perſwade her to ſtay behind, if ſhe went, although ſhe urg'd the unlikelineſs of their Eſcape together, however ſhe would not be contented till ſhe had promis'd to ſend one of <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s Servants for her.</p>
            <p>Now we are forc'd to a ſmall digreſſion, to make you acquainted that the Countrey and all it's Sports, with all the perſwaſions of his Friend <hi>Paneutus,</hi> could not make <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> leave off thinking on his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and it ſo happen'd that his Friend being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in ſome Buſineſs, our melancholy Lover being left to himſelf, who was now taking a turn in the Garden, began to recollect his former Affection, one while chiding himſelf for ſpending ſo long a time in a vain purſuit; another while angry with himſelf for leaving off now, when he was ſo far engag'd, and then a few muſty Apothegms got in his Head, <hi>viz.</hi> Maids ſay No, and take it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he reſolves to renew the Onſet, for which he could not have met with a convenienter time, <hi>Paneutus</hi> being out of the way, for had he been at home, he could not have been brought to have parted with <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> whoſe company he took very much delight in: This being reſolv'd on, he marched to the Stable, and charges the Groom immediately to make ready his Gelding, under pretence of breathing him that Evening,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:187972:13"/>and indeed ſo he did, for in half an hour and two minutes, he reach'd the door of his dearly belov'd <hi>Myrtilla.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyleus</hi> you muſt know, thinking he had been too ſoon, had taken a turn down to view the Caſtle, thinking immediately to come back, and indeed it was not long e're he did, but however this is the critical minute, when out came <hi>Myrtilla</hi> in a riding Dreſs, making ſigns of diſpatch to <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> who was ſtaring on the Windows as he us'd to do, not dreaming what good luck was approaching him; Make haſt, make haſt my Dear (cryes the kind Lady) my Mother elſe will be here immediately. Our Gallant could ſcarce believe his Eyes or Ears, and thought certainly he was a dreaming, for he could never hope for ſuch a happineſs as to have his cruel Lady ſubmit her ſelf to him; but he now began to ſmell out the Plot, and without more adoe helpt the Lady up, who had not as yet diſcern'd the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. Having got his rich Prize behind him, he thought it not ſafe to tarry there long, wherefore ſpurring on his free Beaſt, away he rides, and met with no obſtacle, for the City gates were kept open for <hi>Hyleus,</hi> by the appointment of the Servants, who had brib'd the Watch-men (for you may aſſure your ſelf in <hi>Comus</hi>'s City, they keep very good Hours, although the Citizens are commonly ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliz'd for Revelling, or letting their Wives tarry up longer then themſelves.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyleus</hi> was now return'd back to <hi>Myrtilla's</hi> Door, to which he was no ſooner come, but he heard all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:187972:13"/>the Houſe in an uproar; for it ſeems the old Lady had miſt her Daughter, and began to gheſs at the Buſineſs, for which ſhe was ſchooling <hi>Circe</hi> moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, who being in her riding Clothes, expecting <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s man, could not poſſibly frame any thing like an Excuſe, at which her Miſtreſs was ſo enrag'd, ſhe began to ſeek for ſomething to chaſtice the poor Maid. <hi>Circe</hi> therefore ſeeing her ſcarce avoidable Doom, runs out pulling the door after her, which hinder'd her Executioners purſuit. <hi>Hyleus</hi> who had been all this while in an Agony for his Lady, to think what would become of her, ſeeing <hi>Circe</hi> eſcaping out ſo boldly, and taking her for <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> lights ſtrait off his Horſe to help her up, which done, away he rides. He was no ſooner got through the City Gate, but his Servants that accompany'd him thither, came out to congratulate his good fortune, he was ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd with his Booty, he could ſcarce find time to thank them, making homewards with all the ſpeed imaginable. Whither he was ſcarce come, when by his order three Maids met them ſtrowing Flowers all the way home, while others there were buſied in providing the Cake and Sack-Poſſet; at the Gate ſtood a proper Gentleman Uſher to take down the Lady, Madam Chamber-maid; that done, off leaps <hi>Hyleus</hi> to ſalute her, and bid her welcome to her Own.</p>
            <p>And now at laſt it was that the miſerable man perceiv'd his Errour, but he was wonderfully ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee <hi>Circe,</hi> where he expected <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> he began now to conſider how improbable it was, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:187972:14"/>ſhe ſhould give her ſelf up to him ſo eaſily, and now concludes it was a Plot of <hi>Circe's,</hi> to whom he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes himſelf to be clear'd of the doubt. And is it thus, baſe Slut, thou haſt abus'd me, and thy Miſtreſs? was it for your embraces I have taken all this pains and care? were the numerous Pages about Town, that us'd to accompany their Maſters to viſit my dear <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> grown ſo ſcarce, that I muſt be made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty? I wonder thy impudence could ever harbour ſuch a thought, ſo prejudicious to thy Lady, as to think I was reſerv'd for thy tooth; how cam'ſt thou by this Jewel, which I am confident belong'd once to <hi>Myrtilla?</hi> For none ſure would buy thy favour at the vaſt expence of ſo rich a Diamond? He would have gone on in his tedious Harangue, but being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kind hearted to Females, he began to conſider how unmanly it was to quarrel with a Woman, and for a fault Love had made her commit. However, his paſſion proceeded ſo far that he call'd her Whore: Poor <hi>Circe</hi> who all this while ſtood ſhivering for fear (though it ſeem'd to her a pleaſant pain, being in the company of her ſweet <hi>Hyleus</hi>) was ſomething mov'd at the laſt word, which made a deeper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on her mind, then all had paſt before (for though I will not ſwear for her, yet I think ſhe was honeſt) ſhe makes him this Anſwer. My kindneſs in helping young Gentlemen in Addreſſes to my Lady, could never deſerve that name. No, no, Sir, you have here no Whore, nor one that had any deſigns upon you, but what were innocent and devoted to the Service of my young Miſtreſs. I will not indeed ſo far
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:187972:14"/>bely my Conſcience, as to deny I lov'd you; but I was ſo far from promoting my love, that I quite deſpair'd of it; and therefore reſolv'd to be happy in the next degree, namely, in mediating with you for my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. The deſire of following her hath thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd me to your cenſure. And is <hi>Myrtilla</hi> gone before, then? ſaid <hi>Hyleus;</hi> Yes Sir, anſwered <hi>Circe,</hi> ſhe is, and had not your Paſſion tranſported you, you might e're this have been in a Capacity of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering my Lady, who cannot be gone far.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Circe's</hi> Anſwer you'l ſay was very excuſable, and indeed <hi>Hyleus</hi> could not but approve of it, although anger for his raviſh'd Miſtreſs would not let him at preſent acknowledge it. For he immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Horſes to be brought out of the Stable again, but hold, I think they were not yet put in, and with his other Fellow Travellers like a Knight Errant, reſolves to go to reſcue the Lady, leaving poor <hi>Circe</hi> again to the mercy of the Butler, who was now reſolv'd to try the utmoſt ſtrength of his ſtrong Beer Philter on the weak Virgin. But ſhe, contrary to his expectation, ſeem'd more coy, as having more hopes then ever of marrying <hi>Hyleus,</hi> in caſe her Miſtreſs could not be found out. But we muſt be found as uncivil as <hi>Hyleus,</hi> and leave her to the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers managing, and mad he to his Progreſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Chereſtratus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who by this being ten miles out of Town, was impatient to ſee and ſalute his ſweet Prey, whoſe Maiden-modeſty not ſuffering her to ſpeak firſt, very much wonder'd at her ſilent Lover. They were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:187972:15"/>ſcarce gone a quarter of a mile further; but the tranſparent Rays of the bright Queen of Night (a rare expreſſion for Moon ſhine this ſame) made diſcovery of a delicate pleaſant Meadow, which lay juſt by the Road-ſide. <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> could not for his life paſs by this opportunity, he light and gently taking <hi>Myrtilla</hi> off the Horſe, began the amorous Prologue with a Kiſs. That done, Madam, ſaid he, how happy have you made the late miſerable <hi>Chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus!</hi> At the name of <hi>Chereſtratus, Myrtilla</hi> ſtarted, and looking upon him ſeriouſly, knew him to be the perſon nam'd. The poor Lady was ſo extreamly troubled at this unexpected Accident, that ſhe ſwoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away in <hi>Chereſtratus</hi>'s Arms, and truly me thinks it was ominous, for ever ſince that night the Lady was troubled with Qualms. But I fear I ſhall be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd for playing thus with a Gentlewomans miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; all I have to excuſe it is, that knowing the the fifth Act of the Play and how they came off, it is pardonable to be merry, and laugh before as ſhe did after ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> you may imagine was in a ſweet kind of taking to think that he had loſt his Miſtreſs before he had her (which was true enough, if you can make it out) beſides a Conſtable and a grave igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Jury came in his head, for ſome might think he had kill'd her, beſides the plaguy fear of being wrote againſt, like <hi>Philaſter</hi> for being the death of his pretty Miſs. All this conſider'd, the poor man was extreamly put to his ſhifts, what to do. And though men ſay our wits are beſt in caſes of neceſſity,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:187972:15"/>he at preſent could not think of a better Remedy, then <hi>Hudibras</hi>'s, ſo that he was forc'd to give her a gentle twinge oth' Noſe, for Water in that place there was none, nor any thing elſe that might conduce to the recovering of a Lady out of that ſad condition. <hi>Myrtilla</hi> by this was ſomething come again to her ſelf, and gave <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> ſome ſmall hopes of her, to whom in a lamentable tone ſhe ſaid. By what Magick, Villian, haſt thou depriv'd me of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of my dear <hi>Hyleus?</hi> who were he but preſent, would teach you better manners, then to lie Eves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropping thus, to betray the ſecrets of miſerable Lovers. But alas, why blame I you? It was my own raſhneſs, for which I am juſtly puniſh'd, ſince I could not diſtinguiſh betwixt the Worthy <hi>Hyleus</hi> and the baſe <hi>Chereſtratus.</hi> Our Gallant, that thought himſelf well enough to paſs, as never having a Rupture, or any thing elſe that might reduce him to the uſing the Wedding Ring the wrong way, in caſe Art had conquer'd Nature, could not endure to hear <hi>Myrtilla</hi> preferr <hi>Hyleus</hi> ſo much before him, and was going to vindicate himſelf when thus ſhe continued. O my unhappy Fate! have I for this prov'd diſobedient, and left my old Mother? to fall into the hands of him I ſo much hated, who is in pretence only a Lover? if it be not ſo as I ſay, prove your Affection, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem your fault by killing the miſerable <hi>Myrtilla.</hi> Faintly he thought ſhe ſpoke, for all the while— ſtay, I think there was no ſmile in the caſe; however <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> who came <hi>communi Animantium appetitu,</hi> did not care to ſatisfie his Lady in that point, and had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:187972:16"/>rather get the King a Souldier, then loſe him a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, for Ladies do good Service. No, Madam, ſaid he, that were to injure you, and rob my ſelf of the greateſt happineſs in the world. Your misfortunes are not ſuch, as to make you boldly wiſh for Death, that Bug-Bear to all Ladies. 'Tis time enough for it yet, you have no reaſon to think on't, being in the hands of a Perſon, of whoſe incivility you never yet had any proof. I cannot imagine you are really angry, when if you are pleas'd to remember I took you up in a ready Dreſs for the March, as if you as well as Heaven were willing to make me happy. For doubtleſs, Madam, it was not by meer chance, I left my Friend in the Countrey at ſo unſeaſonable time of Night to come and viſit your door, where unlookt for, my good Genious had prepar'd me a ſight of my divine <hi>Myrtilla.</hi> No, no, the Powers above, whoſe will we ought not to reſiſt, ordain'd this, to ſee how happy they could make a mortal Man by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a perſon ſo nigh their Divinities, as your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable ſelf. This done, he put his Handkerchief to his Eyes, and us'd ſuch comforting expreſſions to the Lady, that they diſſipated her clouds of Sorrows. Her Eyes ſhot ſuch luſtre, that the Moon with all the noiſe of Braſs Pots and Kettles that could be rung out fear'd an Eclipſe. To be ſhort, ſhe ſeem'd ſo well ſatisfy'd, that <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> tying his Horſe to a Tree, did not much offend her, in deſiring her to repoſe her ſelf on a neighbouring Bank. They were no ſooner ſat down, but our Gallant began before his Miſtreſs to admire the works of Nature in that pleaſant place,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:187972:16"/>in whoſe commendations he inſiſted ſo far, that ſoon after he forc'd her to yield to ſome Arguments he brought. He ſhow'd her all the pretty Sceletons, the fair Flowers I mean, that once were Bodies of young Men and Ladies, and turn'd into that fading condition for denying their Admirers ſome ſmall Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie or other. He might have gone on longer, for ſeriouſly the place was ſo pleaſant that it is impoſſible to imagine any thing beyond it in natural Bravery. <hi>Adonis</hi>'s Garden, and whatever Antiquity hath made famous for Pleaſures, could not reach it. I would have ſtrove for a little Poetry, but that at preſent I I am not in the Humour, but if I make a modern Poet of ours deſcribe it better then perhaps I ſhould have done, I ſuppoſe 'tis all one.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>NAture is wanton here, and the high way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seem'd to be private, though it open lay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As if ſome ſwelling Lawyer for his health,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or frantick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer to tame his wealth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had choſen out ten miles — to try</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Two great effects of Art and Induſtry.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ground they trod, was Meadow fertile land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>New trim'd and levell'd by the Mowers hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Above it grew a Rock, rude, ſteep and high,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which claims a kind of Reverence from the Eye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Betwixt 'em both there glides a lovely ſtream</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not loud but ſwift. Meander was a Theam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crooked and rough, but had the Poets ſeen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strait and even (for I have forgot the name) it had immortal been,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:187972:17"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>This ſide the open Plain admits the Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To half the River then did Silver run:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The other half ran clouds, where the curl'd Wood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With his exalted head threatned the flood,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>They had not been in this delightful Scene long, but <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> found his Lady's mind to ſympathize with the pleaſantneſs of the place, which ſo reviv'd on a ſudden her drooping Spirits, that ſhe ſeem'd ſo brisk, airy and gay, as gave our Gallant good hopes that the thoughts of <hi>Hyleus</hi> were remov'd, and that ſhe had no ſmall Affection for him, who was now mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing how to compaſs the great deſign, for the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which he thought nothing more efficacious, then the diſparagement of <hi>Hyleus,</hi> his Rival. Madam, cries he, you cannot now but be ſatisfied how noble all my actions have been to you, far beyond <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s, by whoſe unpardonable neglect I have now the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of ſeeing my dear <hi>Myrtilla.</hi> Lovers, Lady, are ſeldome ſlow when invited by their Miſtreſſes, which makes me confident <hi>Hyleus</hi> had only an intent to abuſe and diſgrace you, who had not the hours above ſent me to that happy Station, your door, had been expos'd to the cenſure of the Neighbours, beſides the Anger you might have incurr'd from the old Gentlewoman your Mother. Ungrateful man, that could diſeſteem ſo great an obligation!</p>
            <p>Theſe words ſo wrought upon her, that ſhe became more obliging than before, ſo that ſhe very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſantly render'd thanks to her Lover for his true Affection, and vow'd ſhe would never have an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:187972:17"/>eſteem for his Rival, which was all the recompence ſhe could make him. No, Madam, (reply'd <hi>Chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus</hi>) if I have deſerv'd any thing of you, you may ſoon think of a better way of rewarding your Lover; who for all thoſe favours he ſaw you daily heap on the unworthy <hi>Hyleus,</hi> could not diminiſh his Affections to you, which muſt now be rewarded, or he will ſacrifice his miſerable life before you. Then taking out a true <hi>Bilbo</hi> blade, that had never kill'd a man yet, and therefore wanted ſeaſoning, he ſet it to his Breaſt, and deſir'd his Sentence. The tender-hearted Lady that but juſt now deſir'd to die her ſelf could not endure to ſee her Lover fall a Victim at her feet, and reſolv'd to withſtand man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, ſaid. Hold, Sir, your caſe is not ſo deſperate, nor I hope your love for me ſo little, as to kill him I eſteem, thy ſelf I mean, my dear <hi>Chereſtratus.</hi> And aſſure your ſelf, that you or no man, ſhall be the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſhall make me happy. Our young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man could not have deſir'd a more ſatisfactory Anſwer from his Lady, to whom (putting up his naked tool) he reply'd. Then, Madam, aſſure your ſelf, you have beſtow'd your favours on one that will ſtudy to deſerve them, while the careleſs <hi>Hyleus</hi> ſhall die with envy at my good fortune: After the Peace thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded between both parties, there paſs'd many amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Dialogues, all which were begun and ended with a ſweet Kiſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Myrtilla</hi> you muſt underſtand, whether entic'd by his pretty diſcourſe, or mov'd with an equal deſire, ſeem'd extraordinary loving, ſo that <hi>Chereſtratus</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:187972:18"/>could not but put forward, had he been leſs modeſt then he was. At my firſt view I was extreamly amaz'd, for, but that I had ſeen the Moon with all her twinkling Attendance, I ſhould have ſworn I ſaw the Lady <hi>Aurora</hi> in one of her richeſt Vermilion Sutes. For it ſeems ſomething that <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> had ſaid in her Ear, had dy'd her Cheeks with a Roſie bluſh. I expected now ſhe ſhould have rattled him ſoundly, but it ſeems ſhe was not ſo angry as I took her for: They continued their Diſcourſe for ſome time, which though I could not hear; I ſoon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it was no Treaſon they ſpoke; for ſoon after I ſaw <hi>Myrtilla</hi> with ſmall reluctancy receive a Green Gown from her luſty Lover, who was now prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to make his Lady amends to the utmoſt of his power for her former Favours. We will leave 'em in mutual Embraces, and inſtead of an <hi>Epithalamium</hi> (for I am loth to be idle) make an Apology for their not ſtaying the Parſon's leiſure. To which theſe grave Reaſons induce them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here the Bride-groom is ſure next morning to have all his Ribbons upon his Breeches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Bride, or the Woman lay with, will not be at a loſs to find her Stockings, which at Ceremonious Weddings are thrown over her Head, nor will her Pins be loſt to dreſs her with.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, While they lie on the Graſs, they need not fear cutting the Bed-cords, or ſowing the Sheets together.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There can be no Bell under their Bed, unleſs a natural Blew-Bell.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:187972:18"/>
            <p>Fifthly, The Lady need not be put to the bluſh the next morning by a company of her Chronies with asking her how ſhe does, and how ſhe likes it.</p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, No troubleſome crowd of Fidlers betimes in the morning, to ſpoil better ſport with their miſerable ſcraping. For theſe and ſome other Reaſons, our Lovers may deſerve your pardon, which I queſtion not but you will give them without peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> now began to fail in his vigour, and was ſounding a Retreat in a whole Volly of Kiſſes, which ſhe return'd very willingly, as being now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of the Obligation ſhe had to him. And then they ſetled themſelves for a gentle Repoſe, which they did in ſo ſweet a poſture, ſhe infolding his Neck in her delicate Arms, that they ſeem'd like <hi>Cynthia</hi> and her belov'd <hi>Endymion,</hi> whoſe ſoft Embraces ſhe ſo oft courted. They had not lain long thus, but a ſweet Sleep ſeiz'd them both, in which they dream'd over again what they had juſt now been the real partakers of. Where we will leave them to their natural Reſt, and return to <hi>Hyleus</hi> and his three Companions, who juſt now unfortunately arriv'd at this Scene of Love, whither they were no ſooner arriv'd, but <hi>Hyleus</hi> ſpy'd out the Pair of Lovers in that loving Condition, that I deſcrib'd them in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyleus</hi> was enrag'd to ſee his <hi>Myrtilla</hi> as it were with her own Conſent given up to another. He immediately draws his Rapier, and ſwears moſt damnably that he will be the death of <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> as in effect he had, but that thoſe who accompany'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:187972:19"/>him, having a kindneſs for his happy Rival, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him to deſiſt from his purpoſe, at leaſt they told him he ought to ſtay till he wak'd, for then he might force him nobly either to reſign up his Life, or his Miſtreſs, ſuppoſing he had forc'd her againſt her Will (as the loving poſture they were in, was proof enough to the contrary) for otherwiſe, it was not worth the while. Well, with much adoe, <hi>Hyleus</hi> was at laſt perſwaded to ſtay till he wak'd, but then he ſwore to be reveng'd on him.</p>
            <p>Hereupon for this purpoſe lighting off their Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they all ſat down by our ſleeping Lovers; It had been you'l ſay, a great temptation to his fellow Travellers to lie by ſo handſome a Lady, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary with accompanying their Maſter in his wilde purſuit, they thus ſeem'd with him rather to have a deſire to ſleep, than any thing elſe; they ſtrove indeed a great while againſt the drowſie Diſtemper, but <hi>Morpheus</hi> at laſt arreſted them, in the King's name, and charg'd them to keep the Peace, which they had broken with their loud Jangling.</p>
            <p>They had not been long under the Leaden Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Gentieman's hands, but the two Lovers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wak'd very much troubled to ſee any Company there, but much more when they knew them to be <hi>Hyleus</hi> and his men. <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> bid his <hi>Myrtilla</hi> not be affraid, but prepare for her Journey, by which he doubted not, but they ſhould eſcape the Enemy, which <hi>Myrtilla</hi> as much now endeavour'd to avoid,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:187972:19"/>as not long before ſhe coveted the Sight of <hi>Hyleus. Chereſtratus</hi> that had before learn'd of <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> that <hi>Hyleus</hi> had receiv'd a rich Diamond of her, which was to be worn in his Hat, was unwilling to leave that Token of his Ladies former Affection behind him, wherefore he advanc'd towards <hi>Hyleus,</hi> and did without any difficulty find out the Jewel by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream luſtre of it. Having got this, he and <hi>Myrtilla</hi> march with full ſpeed together towards his Friend's Houſe, with whom he had lodg'd being invited, the honeſt truſty Soul <hi>Paneutus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had not been long gone, but <hi>Hyleus</hi> and his men awake, and find the Pair of Lovers gone, to the ſatisfaction of all but <hi>Hyleus,</hi> who was ſo much troubled at their eſcape, that they had much adoe to keep him from laying violent hands on himſelf, but his rage was very much encreas'd when he ſaw the Jewel was gone too, and now he reſolves to purſue <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> not as a Rival only, but as a profeſt Enemy. The Servants did all they could to pacifie their furious Maſter, telling him he ought not to be ſo incens'd againſt <hi>Chereſtratus,</hi> ſince he had done nothing but what a Lover in the like caſe would have done, and that doubtleſs it was not his fault, but <hi>Myrtilla</hi> either by her free conſent, or the treachery of <hi>Circe,</hi> that lov'd him her ſelf, had deliver'd her up to him. And that ſince 'twas ſo, he ought not to deſpiſe the innocent flames of pretty <hi>Circe,</hi> who excepting her Birth, ſeem'd altogether as worthy his Bed, as the ſcornful, faithleſs <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla.</hi> What though ſhe ſent that Diamond, yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:187972:20"/>
               <hi>Circe</hi> brought it, by whom he might reckon it given too, ſeeing there was no Remedy left, and there appear'd not the leaſt hopes of overtaking the happy couple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s paſſion was now pretty well over, when he took Horſe for Home, intending to follow his Servants Counſel, and make poor <hi>Circe</hi> happy, who all this while was crying, and deploring her condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As ſoon as he came in, he call'd for her, and with a Kiſs told her, his Intention was to marry her that Night, telling her the mad Adventures of his raſh Journey. <hi>Circe</hi> you may eaſily imagine, was very well pleas'd to hear her Miſtreſs had ſped ſo well, and that ſhe was now to enjoy her belov'd <hi>Hyleus. Hyleus</hi> immediately ſent for the man in Black, and gave order for making ready that very Night for the Wedding, which was done with all ſpeed, and they two huddled to Bed together, for better for worſe, where I ſuppoſe they had as much ſatisfaction of one another, as <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> and <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla</hi> did before, beſides the advantage they had of a ſofter Bed.</p>
            <p>The next day early, <hi>Hyleus</hi> ſent to beſpeak the Wedding Dinner five miles off, where alſo <hi>Chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus</hi> with his Lady were that day to be merry together; and as good luck would have it, they were in the next Room to one another, though neither Company knew of it, till about Dinner time. <hi>Myrtilla</hi> hearing <hi>Hyleus</hi>'s Voice in the next Room, ſwouned, <hi>Chereſtratus</hi> and all his Company
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:187972:20"/>wonder'd at the ſuddeneſs of her ſickneſs, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected there was ſomething in it more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; and as ſoon as ſhe came to her ſelf again, ſhe told them the Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſhe heard <hi>Hyleus,</hi> and fear'd leſt he ſhould know of <hi>Chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus,</hi> and there might ſome miſchief be done. They cheer'd her up, and told her there was no fear of any ſuch thing, eſpecially in that place. While they were comforting <hi>Myrtilla,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was equally a Friend to both of them, ran to tell <hi>Hyleus,</hi> having firſt engag'd him to be civil, ſince things could not be alter'd. <hi>Hyleus</hi> was at firſt ſurprized, but then one glance of <hi>Circe's</hi> diſpell'd his anger, and he was reſolv'd to joyn Companies, which he preſently did, to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of both Parties. Where I'le leave them drinking their Ladies Healths, beſides ſome odd Bruſhers to the little Country Gentleman, or <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla's Hans en Kelder.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187972:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
